<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Motion Planning | Carlos Quintero-Peña</title>
    <link>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/tag/motion-planning/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://carlosquinterop.github.io/tag/motion-planning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Motion Planning</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Motion Planning</title>
      <link>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/tag/motion-planning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Grasps and Placements for Task and Motion Planning in Clutter,</title>
      <link>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/tamp-clutter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/tamp-clutter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Planning for sequential manipulation in robotics is paramount. This is typically achieved by a layered planning approach (called Task and Motion Planning - TAMP) where a &lt;em&gt;skeleton&lt;/em&gt; is computed by a task planner first and then the robot motions for the actions within this skeleton are computed by a motion planner. Before the motions can be computed, continuous values of the action parameters need to be first resolved (this is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;grounding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;). For example, to compute the motion to pick up an object, the grasp pose (i.e. the relative pose of the robot&amp;rsquo;s end-effector with respect to the object) needs to be computed first. To place an object in a surface, the new object location is required. Most TAMP frameworks rely on specialized samplers to obtain these parameters and they do not consider complex geometric constraints that can arise in the presence of cluttered environments. We contribute a specialized grounder for placements and grasps that considers all the actions of a plan skeleton &lt;em&gt;jointly&lt;/em&gt; for problems of planar manipulation under heavy cluttered scenes.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-a-baseline-tamp-with-grounder-based-on-random-sampling-b-our-approach-is-based-on-convex-optimization-of-the-whole-plan-skeleton&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/tamp-clutter/opt-frame_hufbd6a464d4280608a52944d6d37b21c2_201420_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;a) Baseline TAMP with grounder based on random sampling. b) Our approach is based on convex optimization of the whole plan skeleton&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/tamp-clutter/opt-frame_hufbd6a464d4280608a52944d6d37b21c2_201420_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;2364&#34; height=&#34;994&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    a) Baseline TAMP with grounder based on random sampling. b) Our approach is based on convex optimization of the whole plan skeleton
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our grounder is designed to solve problems of planar manipulation, where the robot is required to pick up and place a sequence of objects on a surface and there is potentially many objects of different heights. Additionally, we argue that these problems are hard because they have a very little amount of free space to be used as intermediate placement locations for objects. This setup is similar to a problem known as Object Rearrangement (OR), but unlike OR, we do not assume action feasibility, i.e., the robot hand may collide with another object when placing the grasped object due to their geometry. Additionally, our setup considers other scenarios where objects can be stacked on top of other objects (i.e., high-level actions other than pick and place are considered).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-solution&#34;&gt;Our solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve these problems we propose a specialized grounder that is formulated as an optimization problem over the joint variables of candidate plan skeletons. We describe feasibility constraints (no collision) as non overlapping primitive shapes over conservative approximations of the projections of the robot hand and the objects (see figure below). By performing this simplification, we are able to write problems that can be solved up to global optimality very efficiently. Furthermore, infeasibility of our optimization formulations provides useful information that we use to prune the task space to find plan skeletons that are more likely to be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-geometric-primitives-circles-and-aabbs-are-used-as-conservative-approximations-of-the-robot-hand-and-objects-geometry-on-the-supporting-surface-feasibility-constraints-are-defined-as-non-intersection-of-pairs-of-primitives-along-the-plan-skeleton-the-resulting-optimization-problems-can-be-solved-to-global-optimality&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/tamp-clutter/formulation_huf52dba19cb0c6469a9cf3147d348093a_3336008_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Geometric primitives (circles and AABBs) are used as conservative approximations of the robot hand and objects&amp;amp;rsquo; geometry on the supporting surface. Feasibility constraints are defined as non-intersection of pairs of primitives along the plan skeleton. The resulting optimization problems can be solved to global optimality.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/tamp-clutter/formulation_huf52dba19cb0c6469a9cf3147d348093a_3336008_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;5082&#34; height=&#34;1605&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Geometric primitives (circles and AABBs) are used as conservative approximations of the robot hand and objects&amp;rsquo; geometry on the supporting surface. Feasibility constraints are defined as non-intersection of pairs of primitives along the plan skeleton. The resulting optimization problems can be solved to global optimality.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenging-problems&#34;&gt;Challenging problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed problems are hard due to the high clutter and small amount of free space to place objects. Additional geometric constraints arise when the robot tries to pick up a short object next to a tall object since the robot geometry may collide with the neighbor object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obstructed Pick X (OP-X): a short object that is surrounded by tall objects needs to be grasped and placed in a given goal location. All other objects doe not have a specified goal. This experiment is increasingly hard for high values of X and we show up to OP-9.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chessboard (Chess): The robot needs to set up the blue pieces of the chess in the starting configuration. For each piece, we compute a cylinder that fully contains the mesh representation to express the feasibility constraints and use the circle of its base as geometric primitive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tower Assembling (Tower): The robot needs to assemble a tower with three blocks at a goal location in the given order. Before that, the objects are stacked and therefore they need to be unstacked first. When unstacking them, intermediate locations are needed and other objects on the surface need to be avoided. This is an example of a task that involves highl-level actions other than pick and place (stack and unstack).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aVQhignxBlw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1Cp5NzTTaX0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human-Guided Motion Planning in Partially Observable Environments</title>
      <link>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/blind/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/blind/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is concerned with the problem of motion planning for high-DOF robots under partial observability using guidance from humans.
We have proposed Bayesian Learning in the Dark (BLIND), an algorithm that leverages the human senses to compute high-DOF robot trajectories that are safe despite partial observability of the environment.
The main components that made up BLIND are shown next&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-blind-algorithm&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/blind/BLIND-pipeline_hua1dacfa157fa222ffe93d595be1c08bf_1409506_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;BLIND algorithm&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/blind/BLIND-pipeline_hua1dacfa157fa222ffe93d595be1c08bf_1409506_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;5609&#34; height=&#34;2757&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    BLIND algorithm
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construction of a low-dimensional discrete state space and the guided motion planner are the two main novelties within BLIND.
The former leverages projections and sampling-based motion planners to create a space where reward learning can be performed. The latter uses optimization-based motion planning to incorporate the knowledge learned from the human as motion constraints.&lt;br&gt;
These two together enable reward learning techniques to be used using critiques to learn and compute high-dimensional safe trajectories despite the incomplete environmental information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results show that BLIND outperforms state-of-the-art methods in teaching effort, success rate and path length.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-results-of-simulated-experiments-in-the-box-and-stove-environments&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/blind/results_hu4705a3750929e7e6469c92fb5173704f_331451_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Results of simulated experiments in the Box and Stove environments&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/blind/results_hu4705a3750929e7e6469c92fb5173704f_331451_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1419&#34; height=&#34;674&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Results of simulated experiments in the Box and Stove environments
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our video of a robot implementation of BLIND, where a human user is asked to critique trajectories that are potentially unsafe. BLIND is executed in real-time and it converges to a safe solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RbDDiApQhNo&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motion Planning with incomplete scene information</title>
      <link>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective of the project is to simulate the Fetch robot in a realistic environment considering uncertainty. In order to accomplish this we needed to take into account the complexity of a real robotic platform, starting with the topics covered during the course, i.e., kinematics, dynamics, control, but also others that were either briefly discussed or not at all, such as sensing, localization, motion planning, etc. Instead of building or analyzing all of these from scratch for the Fetch robot, we used a large software stack based on ROS (Robot Operating System). In the project, all of these were integrated in order to solve the problem of successfully planning and executing a grasping task in the presence of uncertain obstacles. The following are the main software components of the solution and a brief description of what was done in this project with each one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gazebo:&lt;/strong&gt; It is the physics simulator where the world and robot are modeled. For the project I created the testing scenes by creating first objects (cylinders in this case) that represent cans and wooden tables. Each graspable object required a grasping pose that the robot knows beforehand that is used to compute the goal configuration for every can. The poses in ROS are represented as a $3D$ vector that represents the position and a $4D$ vector that represents its orientation as a quaternion. The figure below shows an example of one Gazebo scene&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tf2:&lt;/strong&gt; It is a ROS package that provided all the transformations between the different frames in the world. The robot geometry is already known for the the package and the transformations are given as abstract objects that can be operated as we operate transformation matrices. We used these transformations to compute the frame origins of the robot&amp;rsquo;s links that were part of the planned trajectory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MoveIt:&lt;/strong&gt; It is a ROS package that provides access to a set of sampling-based planners available in OMPL. Plans are represented as a sequence of robot states (joint configurations) that are created from the group of joints that is used to plan. For this project we created a group for the 7 arm joints and the torso and therefore, each state could be represented as an 8-dimensional vector. This package also provides controller functions for executing the planned trajectories. The trajectory was required to be time-parameterized before passing it to the controller. The controller also provides a way to receive feedback on whether the given trajectory was successfully executed or not. This was required for the experiments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Octomap:&lt;/strong&gt; It is a library that efficiently stores and manages data that comes from cloud points such as those captured with a RGB-D camera. The octomap represents the world by classifying parts of the space as free, mixed (free/occupied) or unknown. It creates boxes and each box is labeled as one of the possibilities. If the box is empty it stores it with a large resolution, if the box is mixed, it further split it into smaller boxes and it keeps doing that until all are free or occupied or a resolution limit is reached. It was used in this project to represent the scenes. In the experiments, we used a query function to know whether a given point in space was already explored or unknown. The figure below shows a scene representation using octomaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quickhull:&lt;/strong&gt; It is a library that provides fast computation of the convex hull of a set of points in three dimensions. It was required in the project to estimate the swept-out volume of a given trajectory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-scene-and-fetch-robot-in-gazebo-simulator&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/SceneGazebo_hu624e92eda7290956e26acba8c5dafb5e_567015_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Scene and Fetch robot in Gazebo simulator&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/SceneGazebo_hu624e92eda7290956e26acba8c5dafb5e_567015_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1245&#34; height=&#34;864&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Scene and Fetch robot in Gazebo simulator
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;







  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-octomap-representation-of-the-scene-obtained-by-the-on-board-rgb-d-camera-of-the-robot&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/SceneRViz_hu08996a00c9db8f55ee9acda2566b8ddc_179214_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Octomap representation of the scene obtained by the on-board RGB-D camera of the robot&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/SceneRViz_hu08996a00c9db8f55ee9acda2566b8ddc_179214_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1340&#34; height=&#34;874&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Octomap representation of the scene obtained by the on-board RGB-D camera of the robot
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-experiments&#34;&gt;THE EXPERIMENTS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to succeed in the task of planning and executing a motion to grasp an object with sensor data, we needed to improve the scene representation. In many cases, it turned out that the robot was capable of successfully finding a plan but it failed in executing it because the scene was incomplete. This happens because the planner uses unknown space as free. The trivial solution of changing all the unknown space to occupied would not work because it becomes extremely likely that no path would be found since only a small part of the space is actually known by the robot. This assumption is also necessary to allow robots that do not know their entire environment to be able to explore it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows a diagram of the general proposed solution. The idea is to start a plan with the current known scene and then use this plan to extract points that the robot needs to explore before executing the trajectory to make sure that it will succeed (it won&amp;rsquo;t collide). After that, this points are examined to determine whether they are known or not and we command the robot to look at the set of those points that are unknown. Finally, the robot will create a new plan with the updated scene and will repeat this process until finding a safe plan (one where all the interesting points are in known space).&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-diagram-showing-the-main-steps-of-the-proposed-methodology&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/Diagram_hu654b006f9a72dc7f3e05133911643e78_103543_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Diagram showing the main steps of the proposed methodology&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/Diagram_hu654b006f9a72dc7f3e05133911643e78_103543_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1439&#34; height=&#34;1056&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Diagram showing the main steps of the proposed methodology
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to decide which points are interesting to look at, we have explored four different strategies, described below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Object:&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of using the planned trajectory, the robot only looks at the object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixed points:&lt;/strong&gt; The robot looks at two points at each side of the object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frame origins:&lt;/strong&gt; The robot considers all the arm&amp;rsquo;s link origins for all joint configurations of the planned path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swept-out volume:&lt;/strong&gt; The robot considers the volume swept-out by the arm if the trajectory were executed. The volume is estimated by computing the convex hull of consecutive joint configurations in the planned path&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows an image of the robot simulation looking at unknown points of the swept-out volume marked as red arrows. In order to compare the four strategies, we designed the following experiment: we place the robot base in a random position and orientation close to the tables. We randomly choose one can from all in the scene. Then, the robot implements the proposed methodology to create a plan to grasp the selected object using one of the strategies described above and finally the robot executes the trajectory. At that point, there are several possible outputs; the robot is able to succeed in the execution of the trajectory (i.e., it does not collide with obstacles and it reaches the grasping pose), the robot fails in executing the trajectory, the robot can not find a path to solve the problem at hand. For the cases of &lt;strong&gt;frame origins&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;swept-out volume&lt;/strong&gt; strategies, the robot only executes the trajectory when the planner outputs a plan and all the interesting points are in the known region of the space. If the robot makes three planning attempts and it is still not able to find a completely safe path, it takes the risk and executes the current, potentially unsafe plan. This may or may not end up in collision but it is done to make sure that the algorithm won&amp;rsquo;t get stuck in infinite loops and also to avoid excessively large simulation times, especially because there might be points in space that could be occluded.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-fetch-robot-looking-at-interesting-unknown-points-of-the-swept-out-volume-of-the-computed-trajectory&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/Swept-out_hu367fbd22664606b4cec7a0528999f531_644752_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fetch robot looking at interesting unknown points of the swept-out volume of the computed trajectory&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/Swept-out_hu367fbd22664606b4cec7a0528999f531_644752_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1331&#34; height=&#34;1127&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Fetch robot looking at interesting unknown points of the swept-out volume of the computed trajectory
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each strategy was tested when 50 trajectories were executed and the time taken to complete the scene was measured for every strategy. Each motion planning problem is independent of the previous, meaning that the knowledge of the previous scene is not used before solving the next problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;RESULTS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table below show the results of the 50 runs for each strategy. As expected, the simple &lt;strong&gt;object&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;fixed points&lt;/strong&gt; strategies take much less time in looking before executing the planned trajectory since they choose fixed points. However, it can also be seen that their probability of collision is much higher; much more than half of the different trials were not successfully solved. The &lt;strong&gt;frame origins&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;swept-out volume&lt;/strong&gt; strategies effectively increase the probability of succeeding in the task execution since they take into account important points in the planned trajectory. Also, even though they take much more time than the simple strategies, this time is worth in applications where safety is a priority. Finally, these strategies can also create unsafe trajectories since a maximum number of attempts is considered. This number could be increased to further reduce the chances of obtaining unsafe trajectories at the expense of more time taken to look.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-results-of-50-runs-for-the-proposed-methodology-for-completing-the-scene-for-the-4-different-explored-strategies&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/TableResults_hu17d347cdac24f94a8aed3b549cd3788b_83210_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Results of $50$ runs for the proposed methodology for completing the scene for the 4 different explored strategies&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/incomplete-sensing/TableResults_hu17d347cdac24f94a8aed3b549cd3788b_83210_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1051&#34; height=&#34;244&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Results of $50$ runs for the proposed methodology for completing the scene for the 4 different explored strategies
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following video you can see the robot doing the described task for different sets of random scenes. The robot creates a trajectory and then looks at all the important points in the trajectory that are in unknown space (red arrows) until all of them are blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mFQVL0uSuAE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust Motion Planning under Sensing Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Motion planning for high degree-of-freedom ( DOF ) robots is challenging, especially when acting in complex environments under sensing uncertainty. While there is significant work on how to plan under state uncertainty for low- DOF robots, existing methods cannot be easily translated into the high-DOF case, due to the complex geometry of the robot’s body and its environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure above shows an example of a Fetch robot performing manipulation tasks in a table environment. The objects on top of the table are subject to sensing uncertainty in the direction shown by the arrow. The objective is to find a plan to move the green can from its starting position (to the left of the robot) to its goal position, while taking into account the object&amp;rsquo;s uncertainty.
The shown trajectory was computed by our proposed method Robust Optimization-based Motion Planner (ROMP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we have perfect information about the location of objects in a given scene, motion planning methods provide an efficient way to solve our high-DOF manipulation problem. Sampling-based and Optimization-based methods stand out for this task. The former methods, build connectivity information in the robot&amp;rsquo;s configuration space by means of random sample and use such information to find a path between start and goal. The latter methods optimize cost functions that encourage smooth trajectories constrained to stay collision-free. RRT-Connect and TrajOpt are representatives of each category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows top views of Fetch trajectories found by RRT-Connect, TrajOpt and the proposed ROMP, for our manipulation example. Importantly for this application, all planners generate trajectories that go close to the noisy obstacle. This is achieved by using a shortcut heuristic to the plan returned by RRT-Connect. TrajOpt on the other hand naturally encourages short trajectories. It can be seen that ROMP&amp;rsquo;s trajectory stays further away from the noisy object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The target here is not to compare the proposed approach with existing methods. That would not be a fair comparison since they are unaware of the obstacles&amp;rsquo; uncertainty. Our objective is to provide a method to incorporate this type of uncertainty when planning and highlight its benefits compared to not taking the uncertainty into account.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-top-view-of-trajectories-generated-by-different-planners-in-the-manipulation-task&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/FetchFront_hud4235b7ca7007213d0cc402bf8f38ff2_452583_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Top view of trajectories generated by different planners in the manipulation task&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/FetchFront_hud4235b7ca7007213d0cc402bf8f38ff2_452583_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1322&#34; height=&#34;640&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Top view of trajectories generated by different planners in the manipulation task
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-romp-work&#34;&gt;How does ROMP work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROMP can be thought of as an extension of optimization-based planners to account for uncertainty information. It is based on sequential convex optimization (SCO), where the non-convex collision avoidance constraints are linearized around the current solution and a quadratic program is solved at every iteration. A key difference with respect to optimization-based uncertainty unaware planners (e.g., TrajOpt) is that at every iteration of the SCO problem, ROMP creates a robust optimization formulation that protects the solution of the convex subproblem to uncertainty in the problem parameters. The uncertainty of this parameters comes from the uncertainty in the signed distance function between the noisy obstacle and the robot&amp;rsquo;s links and is assumed to be bounded. In its current version, the uncertain parameters lie in a cardinality constrained set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two important aspects make ROMP attractive to be used for robust motion planning. On one hand, it can be applied to high-DOF robots since its formulation leverages the signed distance collision-avoidance constraints proposed by the authors of TrajOpt. Other robust planners in the literature assume that the robot can be modeled as a point in the task space. This assumption works well for applications where the robot&amp;rsquo;s body is small compared to its environment (e.g., drones or small car-like robots), but is not suitable for manipulators made of complex geometry. On the other hand, ROMP does not require the sensing uncertainty to be modeled using Gaussian noise (or other specific type of probability distribution). Its only assumption is that the uncertainty of the parameters is bounded and that one can have access to sample from the distribution. Most methods in the literature require the Gaussianity assumption, which may limit their applicability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At each iteration, ROMP solves the following convex optimization problem:&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-robust-optimization-convex-subproblem-solved-by-romp&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/Formulation_hub51e6b2315bd2a9997b8fad7e1caef64_30633_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Robust Optimization convex subproblem solved by ROMP&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/Formulation_hub51e6b2315bd2a9997b8fad7e1caef64_30633_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;181&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Robust Optimization convex subproblem solved by ROMP
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parameters of this robust formulation need to be estimated at every iteration. This can be achieved by allowing ROMP to sample from the distribution of the noisy objects and keeping the maximum deviation of each parameters from its expected value. ROMP also modifies the actual merit function to account for the additional robust terms being added to the convex subproblems to enable convergence of the SCO algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-experiments&#34;&gt;Some experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We performed experiments to assess the performance of ROMP to a different set of noise models. To this end, we created a nominal scene of the fetch robot example and solved the motion planning problem using RRT-Connect, TrajOpt and ROMP. Then, we evaluated the probability of collision of such trajectories for both Gaussian and Uniform noise for a wide set of the distribution parameters using Monte Carlo experiments for 5000 samples for each distribution. The results can be shown in the figure below:&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-monte-carlo-results-for-the-uncertain-motion-planning-manipulation-task&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/fetch_translational_results_hu91884ff7bef662116ba39e4cb4d3a611_204645_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Monte Carlo results for the uncertain motion planning manipulation task&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/fetch_translational_results_hu91884ff7bef662116ba39e4cb4d3a611_204645_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1753&#34; height=&#34;497&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Monte Carlo results for the uncertain motion planning manipulation task
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be seen that ROMP successfully maintain a low probability of collision for all the distribution parameters (Gaussian on the left, Uniform on the center). Additionally, the figure on the right shows the average distance to collision between the robot and the noisy object for each trajectory waypoint and its standard deviation for both TrajOpt and ROMP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure below show examples of more trajectories computed by the planners for the same task but when the grasp pose is different.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-robust-optimization-convex-subproblem-solved-by-romp&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/FetchTop_hue0ec0193e3d4fa08636043586b129210_444430_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Robust Optimization convex subproblem solved by ROMP&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://carlosquinterop.github.io/project/sensing_uncertainty/FetchTop_hue0ec0193e3d4fa08636043586b129210_444430_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_3.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1663&#34; height=&#34;760&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Robust Optimization convex subproblem solved by ROMP
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be noticed that similar to the previous example, RRT-Connect and TrajOpt find trajectories that go very close to the obstacle. ROMP however, pushes the trajectory closer to the robot&amp;rsquo;s body to account for the uncertainty in the direction of the noise. The following video shows the trajectory traces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IUuDnYvw2Ow&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
